There's this amino acid sarcasine that
starves your cells to make your muscle
cells grow. Now, I get it. You hear the
word starve and you think, "How in the
world can we not give our cells what
they need and yet they'll grow?" And
it's especially confusing when it's in
people dealing with sarcopenia, a
condition characterized by muscle
weakness and reduced muscle size. Like,
we're all prone to experience with age
if we're not careful. Well, it might
seem counterintuitive, but this
particular amino acid works through
strange ways. I just mentioned how
sarcopenia is a problem as we age
because it's characterized by low muscle
mass, reduced muscle strength and power
as well as increased overall frailty of
the body. And we know that people
suffering from sarcopenia have low
sarcasmine levels. The orange condition
is the sarcasene levels in the circenic
individuals. So this study aimed to find
out not only what can be done but if
supporting sarcasmine levels in the body
might reverse signs of sarcopenia.
Because of the time scale of sarcopenia
occurring over many years. The
researchers use old mice and fed them
sarcasine to see if it had any effect
whatsoever. They ended up showing that
sarcasine does increase muscle mass,
implicating sarcasene deficiency
directly as being a factor of severe
muscle loss with aging. Now, while
that's interesting, what if I told you
that sarcasine wasn't acting on the
muscle itself, at least not here. In
fact, sarcasine on the face of it
massively increases the inflammation
inside the tissues of the body like fat
tissue and muscle tissue. So think of
immune cells infiltrating between the
cells that make up those tissues.
Doesn't sound too good, does it? So why
are they suddenly having a block party
in your body? Well, immune cells being
in an area are like police officers in
an area. They could be in a
pro-inflammatory state like an officer
in an arrest mindset or an
anti-inflammatory state like an officer
in a support mindset. They both serve a
function, but they have vastly different
effects on the surrounding area. In this
case, fat tissue or the block party. In
this case, the immune cells are in an
anti-inflammatory state. So, the main
points are so far that sarcasene levels
are low in sarcopenia, a muscle loss
disorder that occurs with age, at least
in part. But supplementing with
sarcasine improves muscle size. But it
also leads to an infiltration of immune
cells into the tissues of the body for
as of yet unknown reasons except we know
that they're in an anti-inflammatory
state. Then why are they amassing
specifically when sarcasine is given?
That's because sarcasine enters the
immune cells and starves them in a
specific manner. Which is why we talked
about starvation earlier. Sarcasine
enters the cells then reduces the
concentration of specific amino acids.
It does that through interfering with
the immune cells ability to uptake amino
acids. That deficiency gets sensed
inside the macrofase the immune cell and
it drives an anti-inflammatory signaling
cascade within the cell. All right. But
how does that impact the muscles of the
body? Well, in circenia and with aging
as a whole, there can be enhanced
inflammation. The immune system is more
activated, doing more damage, wreaking
havoc. The muscle cells are constantly
bombarded by insults. You're ugly. My
96-year-old grandma can outlift you. You
call that a muscle? Emotionally and
importantly, physically. Now, if
sarcasine is able to create more
anti-inflammatory environment close to
the tissue, it might be able to lessen
the noise, at least on the physical
insults. may not really be able to do
much about the emotional ones. And in
fact, the researchers used a muscle
injury model to show that when sarcasine
is supplemented, there is less muscle
cell death and faster muscle
regeneration. Muscle regeneration seen
here. The vertical axis is the muscle
regeneration area. So initially it's
greater and later on it leads to much
smaller areas of regeneration necessary
because this is in conjunction with
other data indicates sarosine speeds up
the muscle recovery. Now that's all
possible because of the
anti-inflammatory immune cells rush into
the musculature just like they do with
the fat tissue and reduce inflammation
thereby reducing the additional damage
but also fostering a healing
environment. Let me quick interject my
opinion here. I'm not a fan of this
model simply because I don't think that
using a muscle injury model is all that
representative of sarcopenia.
It seems more representative of muscle
distrophe or an actual injury. That
doesn't negate the impact that sarcasene
has and it clearly would still benefit
the body in sarcopenia, but I don't like
the model used to make that connection.
Still, the main point here is that
sarcasine enters the immune cells,
reduces other amino acids from being
taken up by the immune cells, which
turns them to an anti-inflammatory
state. Once in that state, they help the
body, fat, and muscle tissue be less
inflammatory, but also recover and
regenerate more quickly. Now, knowing
all that, how can we apply this? Well,
if you've ever been interested in
learning how sarcasine affects the fat,
tissue, and the liver, or exactly how
sarcasine selectively starves the immune
cells, or even how it directly
influences muscle regeneration and some
alternative supplements to combat
sarcopenia, check out the extended
version of this video that you're
watching. It covers all of that, plus
more. And you'll get all these goodies
included, all available as a Physic
Insider member. The link to join is in
the description. I hope to see you
there. So we know there is an
association between significantly
reduced muscle mass and function with
age and low sarcasine levels as we went
over initially. However, there are no
human randomized control trials on
sarcasine supplementation and muscle.
Although sarcasine supplements are
available. I'm mentioning
supplementation from the top because
almost no food has any appreciable
amounts of sarcas. So like eggs, turkey,
ham, legumes, steak have some but in
tiny amounts that aren't worth bothering
with. On the other hand, while there
have been human randomized control
trials using sarcasine, although they
aren't in muscle outcomes, they are in
psychiatric conditions. This is
difficult to then carry over to what
we've been discussing here. Plus, we
don't know enough about the possible
negatives of supplementation to really
want to focus on it. That limits us a
lot, but not completely because your
body produces sarcasine. It's probably
the main, if not only reason that
sarcasine levels drop. So, could we
potentially support sarcasmine
production? Well, possibly. Sarcasine is
produced from glycine and a tagged
methionine. These are both amino acids
that we consume from protein sources. It
can also be produced by removing a tag
off of another nutrient called choline.
I won't beat you over the head with the
biochemistry, but is it possible that
consuming sufficient amounts of these
amino acids and choline could support
sarcasmine production in the body? Yeah,
it's possible. I'm going to cover some
more on this stuff for the insiders if
you're interested. Now, I'm a bit
hesitant here because we're making some
assumptions and taking some leaps that I
don't like to take. The reality is that
you currently have a few options. One,
supplement with sarcasine where the
research is weak and we don't know the
consequences. Number two, prioritize
foods and protein sources that contain
glycine, methinine, and choline with the
hope that this might translate into
greater sarcasine levels. I realize this
isn't as solid as some other analyses
that I've done, but I'm not a fan of
extending beyond what we have. And this
is what we currently have until further
research releases. But honestly, when it
comes down to it, I think I'd massively
overindex on exercise over trying to
optimize sarcasmine based on where the
literature is. Considering that we're
discussing sarcopenia, the rewards will
be manyfold greater. I really have to
add that. So we have some evidence that
sarcasine levels are reduced in people
with age related muscle loss and
strength called sarcopenia. We see that
sarcasine leads to an anti-inflammatory
profile while encouraging immune cells
to infiltrate our tissues and reduce the
inflammatory damage. It also helps in
muscle regeneration and recovery.
However, human evidence is limited and
not muscle focused. So we need more
research before we can really jump into
the whole supplementation area. Although
a few psychiatric studies have used
supplementation. Another way to ensure
sarcasine is to support its production
in your body through sufficient glycine,
methane, and choline consumption.
Deficiency likely would reduce
sarcasine, but more of all beyond
necessary intakes is unknown if it'll
actually raise sarcasmine more.
Ultimately, this is exciting research,
but it's early days. But there are more
established ways of combating sarcopenia
that are far less speculative right
here.